<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Bioinformatics Tools &amp; Papers</title><link>https://adoni5.github.io/workflow-rss/</link><description>Curated bioinformatics papers and tools</description><item><title>Context-aware transcript quantification from long-read RNA-seq data with Bambu</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-023-01908-w</link><description>Nature Methods — Chen, Sim, Wan, Yeo, Lee, Ling, Love, Göke</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 16:02:21 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-transcriptomes</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-023-01908-w</guid></item><item><title>Identification of cell barcodes from long-read single-cell RNA-seq with BLAZE</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-023-02907-y</link><description>Genome Biology — You, Prawer, De Paoli-Iseppi, Hunt, Parish, Shim, Clark</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 11:04:44 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-transcriptomes</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-023-02907-y</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:p&gt;Long-read single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) enables the quantification of RNA isoforms in individual cells. However, long-read scRNA-seq using the Oxford Nanopore platform has largely relied upon matched short-read data to identify cell barcodes. We introduce BLAZE, which accurately and efficiently identifies 10x cell barcodes using only nanopore long-read scRNA-seq data. BLAZE outperforms the existing tools and provides an accurate representation of the cells present in long-read scRNA-seq when compared to matched short reads. BLAZE simplifies long-read scRNA-seq while improving the results, is compatible with downstream tools accepting a cell barcode file, and is available at &lt;jats:ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/shimlab/BLAZE"&gt;https://github.com/shimlab/BLAZE&lt;/jats:ext-link&gt;&lt;jats:bold&gt;.&lt;/jats:bold&gt;&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>Accurate isoform discovery with IsoQuant using long reads</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-022-01565-y</link><description>Nature Biotechnology — Prjibelski, Mikheenko, Joglekar, Smetanin, Jarroux, Lapidus, Tilgner</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 17:02:56 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-transcriptomes</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-022-01565-y</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:p&gt;Annotating newly sequenced genomes and determining alternative isoforms from long-read RNA data are complex and incompletely solved problems. Here we present IsoQuant—a computational tool using intron graphs that accurately reconstructs transcripts both with and without reference genome annotation. For novel transcript discovery, IsoQuant reduces the false-positive rate fivefold and 2.5-fold for Oxford Nanopore reference-based or reference-free mode, respectively. IsoQuant also improves performance for Pacific Biosciences data.&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>Repun: an accurate small variant representation unification method for multiple sequencing platforms</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbae613</link><description>Briefings in Bioinformatics — Zheng, Ren, Chen, Wong, Li, Yu, Lam, Luo</description><pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 11:46:39 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-human-variation</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbae613</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;Ensuring a unified variant representation aligning the sequencing data is critical for downstream analysis as variant representation may differ across platforms and sequencing conditions. Current approaches typically treat variant unification as a post-step following variant calling and are incapable of measuring the correct variant representation from the outset. Aligning variant representations with the alignment before variant calling has benefits like providing reliable training labels for deep learning-based variant caller model training and enabling direct assessment of alignment quality. However, it also poses challenges due to the large number of candidates to handle. Here, we present Repun, a haplotype-aware variant-alignment unification algorithm that harmonizes the variant representation between provided variants and alignments in different sequencing platforms. Repun leverages phasing to facilitate equivalent haplotype matches between variants and alignments. Our approach reduced the comparisons between variant haplotypes and candidate haplotypes by utilizing haplotypes with read evidence to speed up the unification process. Repun achieved &amp;amp;gt;99.99% precision and &amp;amp;gt; 99.5% recall through extensive evaluations of various Genome in a Bottle Consortium samples encompassing three sequencing platforms: Oxford Nanopore Technology, Pacific Biosciences, and Illumina. Repun is open-source and available at (https://github.com/zhengzhenxian/Repun).&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>Deacon: fast sequence filtering and contaminant depletion</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.06.09.658732</link><description>Unknown Journal — Constantinides, Lees, Crook</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 02:40:11 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-metagenomics</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.06.09.658732</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:sec&gt;&lt;jats:title&gt;Motivation&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:p&gt;Realising the value of large DNA sequence collections demands efficient search and extraction of sequences of interest. Search queries may vary in size from short gene sequences to multiple whole genomes that are too large to fit in computer memory. In microbial genomics, a routine search application involving both large queries and large collections is the removal of contaminating host genome sequences from microbial (meta)genomes. Where the host is human,&lt;jats:italic&gt;sensitive&lt;/jats:italic&gt;classification and excision of host sequences is usually necessary to protect host genetic information.&lt;jats:italic&gt;Precise&lt;/jats:italic&gt;classification is also critical in order to retain microbial sequences and permit accurate microbial genomic analysis. While human pangenomes have been shown to increase sensitivity of human sequence classification, existing bioinformatic host depletion approaches have either limited precision when used with metagenomes or large computing resource requirements.&lt;/jats:p&gt;&lt;/jats:sec&gt;&lt;jats:sec&gt;&lt;jats:title&gt;Results&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:p&gt;We present Deacon, an efficient and versatile sequence filter for raw sequence files and streams. We demonstrate its leading accuracy for the task of host depletion, using less computing resource than existing approaches. By querying a human pangenome index for minimizers contained in each input sequence, Deacon is able to accurately classify and discard diverse human sequences from long reads at over 250Mbp/s with a commodity laptop. We present validation of classification sensitivity, specificity and speed with simulated short and long reads for diverse catalogues of human, bacterial and viral genomes alongside existing methods. Beyond host depletion, Deacon is well suited to common sequence search and filtering applications, particularly those involving large queries. Capable of indexing a human genome in under 30s, Deacon is equipped to rapidly compose custom minimizer indexes using set operations, facilitating efficient search and filtering of massive sequence datasets using gigabase queries.&lt;/jats:p&gt;&lt;/jats:sec&gt;&lt;jats:sec&gt;&lt;jats:title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/jats:title&gt;&lt;jats:p&gt;Deacon is implemented as an MIT-licensed command line tool written in Rust and packaged with Bioconda. Code is available from&lt;jats:ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/bede/deacon"&gt;https://github.com/bede/deacon&lt;/jats:ext-link&gt;.&lt;/jats:p&gt;&lt;/jats:sec&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>Topsicle: a method for estimating telomere length from whole genome long-read sequencing data</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.07.10.664126</link><description>Unknown Journal — Nguyen, Choi</description><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 12:50:14 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-teloseq</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.07.10.664126</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:p&gt;Telomeres protect chromosome ends and its length varies significantly between organisms. Because telomere length variation is associated with various biomedical and eco-evolutionary phenotypes, many biological fields are interest in understanding its biological significance. Here we introduce Topsicle, a computational method that estimates telomere length from whole genome long read sequencing data using k-mer and change point detection analysis. Simulations showed Topsicle was robust to sequencing errors and coverage. Application of Topsicle on plant and human cancer cells showed high accuracy and comparable results to direct telomere length measurements. We predict Topsicle will be a useful tool for studying telomere biology. Topsicle is available at https://github.com/jaeyoungchoilab/Topsicle&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>TARPON - a Telomere Analysis and Research Pipeline Optimized for Nanopore</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.04.22.649940</link><description>Unknown Journal — Deimler, Ho, Norbert, Baumann</description><pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 11:25:13 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-teloseq</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.04.22.649940</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;
            &lt;jats:sec&gt;
               &lt;jats:title&gt;Background&lt;/jats:title&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;Long-read sequencing has transformed many areas of biology and holds significant promise for telomere research by enabling analysis of nucleotide-level resolution chromosome arm–specific telomere length in both model organisms and humans. However, the adoption of new technologies, particularly in clinical or diagnostic contexts, requires careful validation to recognize potential technical and computational limitations.&lt;/jats:p&gt;
            &lt;/jats:sec&gt;
            &lt;jats:sec&gt;
               &lt;jats:title&gt;Results&lt;/jats:title&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;We present &lt;jats:bold&gt;TARPON&lt;/jats:bold&gt; (Telomere Analysis and Research Pipeline Optimized for Nanopore), a best-practices Nextflow pipeline designed for the analysis of telomeres sequenced on the Oxford Nanopore Technologies (ONT) platform. TARPON can be executed via the command line or integrated into ONT’s EPI2ME agent, providing a user-friendly graphical interface for those without computational training. Nextflow’s container-based architecture eliminates dependency conflicts, thereby streamlining deployment across platforms.&lt;/jats:p&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;TARPON isolates telomeric repeat–containing reads, assigns strand specificity, and identifies enrichment probes that can be used both for demultiplexing and for confirming capture-based library preparation. To ensure that the analysis is restricted to full-length telomeres, reads lacking a capture probe or non-telomeric sequence on the opposite end are excluded. A sliding-window approach defines the subtelomere-to-telomere boundary, followed by quality filtering to remove low-quality or subtelomeric reads that passed earlier steps. The pipeline generates customizable statistics, text-based summaries, and publication-ready visualizations (HTML, PNG, PDF). While default settings are optimized for diagnostic workflows, all parameters are easily adjustable via the GUI or command line to support diverse applications. These include telomere analyses in variant-rich samples (e.g., ALT-positive tumors) and organisms with non-canonical telomeric repeats such as some insects (GTTAG) and certain plants (GGTTTAG).&lt;/jats:p&gt;
            &lt;/jats:sec&gt;
            &lt;jats:sec&gt;
               &lt;jats:title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/jats:title&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;TARPON is the first complete and experimentally validated pipeline for Nanopore-based telomere analysis requiring no data pre-processing or prior bioinformatics expertise, while offering flexibility for advanced users.&lt;/jats:p&gt;
            &lt;/jats:sec&gt;</abstract></item><item><title>Echtvar: compressed variant representation for rapid annotation and filtering of SNPs and indels</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkac931</link><description>Nucleic Acids Research — Pedersen, de Ridder</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 10:48:03 +0000</pubDate><category>wf-human-variation</category><type>publication</type><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkac931</guid><abstract>&lt;jats:title&gt;Abstract&lt;/jats:title&gt;
               &lt;jats:p&gt;Germline and somatic variants within an individual or cohort are interpreted with information from large cohorts. Annotation with this information becomes a computational bottleneck as population sets grow to terabytes of data. Here, we introduce echtvar, which efficiently encodes population variants and annotation fields into a compressed archive that can be used for rapid variant annotation and filtering. Most variants, represented by chromosome, position and alleles are encoded into 32-bits-half the size of previous encoding schemes and at least 4 times smaller than a naive encoding. The annotations, stored separately within the same archive, are also encoded and compressed. We show that echtvar is faster and uses less space than existing tools and that it can effectively reduce the number of candidate variants. We give examples on germ-line and somatic variants to document how echtvar can facilitate exploratory data analysis on genetic variants. Echtvar is available at https://github.com/brentp/echtvar under an MIT license.&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract></item></channel></rss>